Michael Johnson

Software Engineer

PROFILE

I'm a full stack engineer who is passionate about programming, people, and teams. I find it rewarding to be a part of what great teams are able to accomplish. I have multiple years of experience in Typescript, Go, Javascript and Ruby.

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Software Engineer -- Umbra

2023 - present

Umbra (umbra-collab.net ∂) is a browser-based code editor with real-time collaboration and code execution.

- Led the design and implementation of the Umbra backend as a scalable, service-oriented architecture, including five discrete services utilizing various hosting solutions to allow for ease of horizontal scalability. (Node.js, Express.js, AWS EC2, Cloudflare Workers, Durable Objects, R2)
- Engineered multiplayer code-editing functionality by leveraging CRDT data structures to allow for conflict resolution and consistent state across users. (Yjs, WebSockets, CRDT)
- Implemented persistence of user 'code snippets' allowing users to save their work to an individualized 'Code Library' by designing an appropriate schema and data layer, and backing Umbra with a relational database running on its own server. (Postgres, SQL, AWS RDS, AWS IAM)
- Created a solution for customer identity and access management that allowed for user account authentication/authorization functionality. (AWS Cognito)
- Automated the deployment process saving many hours of manual-deployment overhead and reducing a 19 step process to a single push command. (GitHub Actions, Docker)
- Designed and implemented service interfaces and a RESTful API for Umbra, supporting user authentication, code snippet management, and real-time code execution.
- Authored a comprehensive case study
 Ø (umbra-collab.net), analyzing Umbra's problem domain, system design, technical challenges and choices, and engineering decisions.
- Collaborated with a remote team of four engineers across three time zones, employing agile methodologies and practices such as daily standups and mob/pair programming.

Software Engineer -- Self-employed

2021 - present

Developed open-source applications including:

- mvfs Lightweight full-text search service (Go, Ngrams, Tokenization, Redis, Reverse Indexing)
- ReqBucket Tool for collecting and debugging webhooks. (DO Droplet, Nginx, MongoDB, Node.js, Express, React)
- vChat Open-source internet chatroom toolkit. (Go, Golang, React)

Sales Manager (Certified Arborist) -- Davey Tree Expert Co.

2020 - 2021

- Managed 31 employees and engaged in daily meetings with crews and crew leaders to delegate jobs.
- Set company sales record for first-year sales arborist and won Davey Sales Award.

Team Leader -- Davey Tree Expert Co.

2017 - 2020

- Led crews of arborists in planning and executing logistically complex and potentially hazardous tree-work jobs.
- Interfaced with clients to communicate regarding expectations and to ensure job-satisfaction.

SKILLS

Backend	Frontend JavaScript, TypeScript, React/Redux,	Cloud	Other
Node.js, Express, Ruby,		VPS, AWS EC2, IAM, RDS,	Docker, Linux, Bash,
Go, PostgreSQL,		Cloudflare Workers,	HTTP, Git, GitHub,
MongoDB, REST APIs	Handlebars, HTML/CSS	Durable Objects, R2	WebSockets, Jest, Nginx

EDUCATION

Launch School Software Engineering	2021 - 2023

Georgia State University -- M.A. (ABT), Philosophy 2010 - 2012

University of Colorado, Boulder -- Graduate Coursework, Linguistics 2011

Mount Vernon Nazarene University -- B.A. Philosophy 2005 - 2009